Francis J. Vail Papers VHP2004/19
CCSU Veterans History Project
Francis J. Vail Papers
Bulk, 1942-1945
1942 - 1945, 2004
VHP2004/19
CCSU Veterans History Project
45.0 Digital objects 1 Interview DVD
Vail, Francis J., 1921 - 2010, Francis James
Biographical/Historical note
Francis "Jim" Vail enlisted in the U.S. Army Air Corps in September of 1942. He was living in Stafford Springs, CT at the time, and applied to be a pilot. Although, he failed the eye test, he wanted to remain in the Air Corps, because it seemed more "exciting" than the infantry. Vail's basic training was in Atlantic City, NJ, just off of the boardwalk. He stayed in the Dennis Hotel, which was next to where the Miss America pageant was staged, and the men in basic training were able to see the entire show from their hotel. From basic training, Vail was sent to the Long Island Institute of Technology to learn airplane mechanics, and lived in an apartment building while going to school. The 16 week program was taught by civilians, and the men in the program lived as civilians for the most part, as they only had one hour a day where instruction was given by the army. Vail was then stationed at Kirtland Air Force Base, NM just after it was built, where he remained for nine months working in the airplane hangar. While stationed there the movie premier for "Bombardier" was held, as it had been filmed primarily on the base, and all of the soldiers were invited to attend. From there, Vail received his orders to go overseas, and shipped out of New Jersey in a convoy of over 100, 000 soldiers. They were sent to Bizerte, Africa to await their orders, and after two weeks, Vail was transferred to Bari, Italy to work as a mechanic at the air field as part of the 41st Air Depot Group. Vail describes what it was like to live on the air base, how it was bombed extensively by the Germans, and what they did for entertainment, including a story about a game the soldiers invented called " donkey softball". The 41st Air Depot Group was shipped home in 1945, and received their orders to return before the war had ended. V - E Day was the day they actually shipped out, and they ended up being one of the first ships to arrive back in the U.S. Although they were shipped home, Vail's service time was not yet up, and he was sent to Spokane, WA to train for the Invasion of Japan. Because the invasion never happened he was stationed at the Newark airport to work as a draftsmen until his discharge. Vail was discharged in late 1945, and although he was offered a job as an airplane mechanic at Bradley airport, he instead took a job as a draftsmen, which he retired from.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Army Air Corps. 41st Air Depot Group.; United States. Army Air Corps.; Atlantic City (N.J.); Bari (Italy); Bombardier (Motion picture); Fort Devens (Mass.); Gioia del Colle (Italy); Kirtland Air Force Base (N.M.); United States. Air Force -- Aviation mechanics; World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Italy
- Series I: Military Documents
  - Aviation cadet examining board letter, n.d.; VHP2004/19.I.1; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Application instructions and check list for appointment as aviation cadet, VHP2004/19.I.2; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Application for appointment as aviation cadet, June 1, 1942; VHP2004/19.I.3; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Honorable discharge papers, October 17, 1945; VHP2004/19.I.4; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Separation qualification record, October 17, 1945; VHP2004/19.I.5; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Certificate of eligibility for benefits of the Servicemen’s Readjustment Act of 1944, 1955; VHP2004/19.I.6
- Series II: Multi-Media
  - Subseries A: Still Images
    - Francis James Vail, Army Air Corps - Stafford Springs, CT, n.d.; VHP2004/19.II.1
    - Air plave crew - Gioia del Colle, Italy, n.d.; VHP2004/19.II.2
    - L-R: Sgt.Haven Williams, Francis Vail, the other three soldiers are unknown - Africa, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.3
    - German attack on Bari, Italy, December 2, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.4
    - After German bombing - Bari, Italy, December 2, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.5
    - Soldiers and civilians searching for bodies after German bombing of Bari, Italy, December 2, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.6
    - B-24 Bomber Aircraft - Italy, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.7
    - Gioia del Colle Air Base - Gioia del Colle, Italy, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.8
    - Gioia del Colle Air Base - Gioia del Colle, Italy, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.9
    - Crew fixing B-24 engine - Gioia del Colle Air Base, Italy, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.10
    - A huge crane working on B-24 bomber - Gioia del Colle Air Base, Italy, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.11
    - B-24 taking off - Gioia del Colle Air Base, Italy, 1943; VHP2004/19.II.12
    - Fuel Tanker - Gioia del Colle Airfield, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.13
    - Italian Child as a camp mascot - Gioia del Colle, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.14
    - R & R. Persons L-R: unknown, unknown, George Norcross, Phil Moskowitz, unknown, Francis Vail, Bill Martinell; squatting in front - Radio operator from Maine. - Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.15
    - B-17 - Gioia del Colle Airfield, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.16
    - Picture of Rome, Italy taken by Francis Vail when on R & R, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.17
    - St. Peter’s Basilica - Rome, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.18
    - Rome, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.19
    - U.S.O. crew at Gioia del Colle, Italy., 1944; VHP2004/19.II.20
    - Crashed B-24 on fire - Gioia del Colle Airfield, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.21
    - Cover for the 41st Air Depot Group designed Francis Vail, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.22
    - Jack Haley christening “Jack Haley’s Comet”, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.23
    - Jack Haley is at right with members of the U.S.O. crew - Gioia del Colle, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.24
    - Jack Haley at right with U.S.O. crew - Gioia del Colle, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.25
    - 5,000th plane made by Ford signed by people who worked on it - Gioia del Colle, Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.26
    - Mussolini’s Youth Camp - Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.27
    - Mussolini’s Youth Camp after the Americans took possession - Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.28
    - Mussolini’s Youth Camp after the Americans took possession - Italy, 1944; VHP2004/19.II.29
    - An aerial view of Mount Vesuvius erupting - Italy, n.d.; VHP2004/19.II.30
    - An aerial view of Mount Vesuvius erupting - Italy, n.d.; VHP2004/19.II.31
    - An aerial view of Mount Vesuvius erupting - Italy, n.d.; VHP2004/19.II.32
    - An aerial view of Mount Vesuvius erupting - Italy, n.d.; VHP2004/19.II.33
    - An aerial view of Mount Vesuvius erupting - Italy, n.d.; VHP2004/19.II.34
  - Subseries B: Moving Images
    - Oral history interview with Francis J. Vail, September 4, 2004; 2004/19.II.B.I; 1.0 dvd (Disk VHP DVD2004/19, Box VHP Interview 1)